A Guide to the Washington Irving Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #6256-m
Washington Irving Collection 1813-1919, n. d.
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
6256-m
122 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Purchase 1964 Mar 19
Item Listing
- Manuscripts
  - Washington Irving's account book, 1840-1845; AMs, 16 p.
  - Receipt book, 1836-1837; AMs, 7 p.
    (includes signature of Washington Irving
  - "Anecdote of the Young Physician", n. d.; AMs, 4 p.
  - "Literary Life", n. d.; AMs, 1 p. (fragment)
  - Notes regarding "Prester John", n. d.; AMs, 4 p.
  - Notes regarding Spanish politics, 1842 Nov 5; AMs, 9 p.
    [not in Washington Irving's hand; possibly a translation of some of his notes]
  - Four unidentified leaves, n. d.; AMs, 4 p. (fragments)
    including second copy of notes regarding "Adam and the Fall"
- Correspondence
  - Sir Walter Scott to Henry Brevoort, 1813 Apr 23; ALS, 2 p. w/addr (facsimile)
  - Thomas Campbell to P[eter] Irving, 1814 Mar 1; ALS, 4 p. w/addr
  - Washington Irving to Henry Brevoort, 1815 May 25; AL, 2 p. (copy)
  - Jane [Frothingham] to John Frothingham, [1816] Sep 29; ALS, 3 p. w/addr
  - Lady Spencer to Washington Irving, 1822 Jun 15; AL, 1 p. w/addr
    (in third person)
  - Washington Irving to [Mrs. John Foster], [1823] Jun 1; AL, 2 p. (copy)
  - Washington Irving to [Mrs. John Foster], [1823] Nov 8; AL, 2 p. (copy)
  - Washington Irving to unknown, [1823 Nov 26]; AL, 2 p. (extract)
  - Washington Irving to Mrs. [John] Foster, 1823 May 4; AL, 2 p. (copy of excerpts)
    (includes following item)
  - Washington Irving to Mrs [John] Foster, 1826 May 7; AL (copy of excerpts)
    with poem, "To Miss Emily Foster on Her Birthday" (copy)
  - T[homas] M[oore] to Washington Irving, [1830]; ALS, 1 p. w/addr
  - Thomas Moore to Washington Irving, 1831 Jan 31; ALS, 1 p. w/addr
  - Thomas Moore to Washington Irving, 1831 Mar 11; ALS, 1 p. w/addr
  - S. M. L[ane] to Washington Irving, [1831 Sep 13]; ALS, 1 p. w/addr
    w/ANS reply from Washington Irving at bottom
  - Thomas Moore to Washington Irving, 1833 Apr 24; ALS, 3 p. w/addr
  - [I. W.] Newton to Washington Irving, [1835 Jul 14]; ALS, 3 p. w/addr
  - W[illiam] S. Libbey to Richard Winfield, [1840] Nov 29; ALS, 3 p. w/addr
  - James Edward Alexander to Washington Irving, 1841 Nov 6; ALS, 3 p. w/addr
  - Ebenezer Irving to Washington Irving, 1842 Mar 17; ALS, 3 p. w/addr
  - Aaron Vail to Washington Irving, 1842 Mar 17; ALS, 4 p.
  - [ Washington Irving] to Mary, 1842 Aug 3; AL, 2 p. w/addr (incomplete, copy)
  - E. L. Cleaveland to William Libbey, et al, 1844 Mar 4; ALS, 4 p. w/addr
    w/trans. of ALS, 1844 Feb 6, E. R. Tucker to E. L. Cleaveland
  - Washington Irving to Gouverneur Kemble, 1847 Jul 8; ALS, 2 p.
  - D. Appleton and Company to Washington Irving, 1847 Sep 9; ALS, 2 p. w/dkt
  - S. W. Halstead to M. Gulliam, 1849 Mar 17; ALS, 3 p.
  - James Beekman to Washington Irving, 1851 Jun 19; ALS, 1 p.
  - Irving Paris to [ Washington Irving], 1851 Oct 13; ALS, 2 p.
  - Receipt signed by John Boyd, from S. K. Burkholder, 1852 Aug 12; ANS, 1 p.
  - [S. F. R.] Abbey to William Libbey, 1854 Sep 23; ALS, 2 p.
  - Mr. Perrin to William Libbey, 1855 May 17; ALS, 1 p.
  - H[enry] T[heodore] Tuckerman to Washington Irving, 1856 Jan 5; ALS, 4 p.
  - Bill of lading goods to be shipped to William Libbey, 1856 Jan 24; DS, 1 p.
  - Washington Irving to [Emily Foster] Fuller, 1856 Jul 2; AL, 2 p. (copy)
  - Joseph Robertson to Pierre Irving, 1856 Sep 1; AL, 6 p. (copy)
  - Joseph Robertson to Pierre Irving, 1856 Sep 30; AL, 6 p. (copy)
  - Irving Van Wart to unknown, 1857 Jul 19; AL, 4 p. (excerpt)
  - S[amuel] Austin Allibone to Washington Irving, 1857 Sep 12; ALS, 2 p.
  - William Lambert to William [Alving], 1858 Jun 28; ALS, 1 p.
  - William Libbey to B. Douglass and Co., 1859 Jan 23; ALS, 1 p.
  - Julia to Helen, 1859 Jan 30; ALS, 8 p.
  - B. Douglass and Co.[ New York] to William Libbey, 1859 Feb 3; ALS, 2 p.
    encl. ALS, same date, B. Douglass and Company[ New York] to B. Douglass and Company[ New Orleans]
  - S. A. F[rothingham] to unknown, 1859 Sep; ALS, 4 p.
  - Pierre Irving to Henry W[adsworth] Longfellow, 1859 Dec 23; ALS, 2 p.
  - Helen to Catherine [Paris] regarding death of Washington Irving, [1859]; ALS, 2 p. (fragment)
  - James Lenox to [Washington] Frothingham, 1860 Jan 3; ALS, 1 p.
  - John D. [Vahoust] to William Libbey, 1861 Feb 4; ALS, 1 p.
  - Kate to Abram, 1862 Jul 20; ALS, 10 p.
  - [_____ Eurowsky] to Madame [______], 1863 Oct 25; ALS, 2 p.
  - E. Hunn, Jr. to Pierre Irving, 1864 Apr 22; ALS, 1 p.
  - J. D. Fish to Pierre Irving, 1864 Apr 24; ALS, 3 p.
  - [ William Libbey] to [ J. Forster], 1874 Jan 12; ALS, 1 p.
  - Henry Alexander to William Libbey, 1874 Nov 20; ALS, 1 p.
  - [Sarah] to Eliza, 1883 Jun 19; ALS, 4 p.
  - Marshall Field to William Libbey, 1886 Dec 22; LS, 2 p.
  - W. W. Sherman to William Libbey, 1890 Feb 24; ANS, 1 p.
    (notice of meeting)
  - John Stewart to William Libbey, 1893 Sep 18; ALS, 1 p.
  - M. R. Pryor to J[ohn] J. McCook, 1895 Nov 22; ALS, 2 p.
  - John J. McCook to Frederick Libbey, 1895 Dec 3; ALS, 1 p.
  - George Irving to Cousin [ Washington Frothingham], 1904 Jun 10; ALS, 4 p.
  - George Irving to Washington Frothingham, 1904 Jun 15; ALS, 2 p.
  - Henry Bellows to Oscar Irving, [Feb 17]; ALS, 3 p. w/env
  - Emily Fuller to [ Pierre Irving], Mar 10; ALS, 4 p.
  - Melville [deLancey] Landon(" Eli Perkins") to [William] Libbey, Jul 12; ALS, 3 p.
  - Julia to Helen, Aug 24; ALS, 4 p.
  - unknown to [his children], Oct 15; AL, 1 p.
  - T. Eames to Mrs. Irving, Oct 29; ALS, 2 p.
  - [ Melville deLancey Landon] to [ William Libbey], ALS, 4 p.
    encl. circular for Landon's new book
  - Maggie to Kitty, n. d.; ALS, 4 p.
  - Washington Irving to unknown, n. d.; AL, 3 p. (extracts)
    regarding Spain
  - T[homas] M[oore] to Washington Irving, n. d.; ALS, 1 p. w/addr
  - T[homas] M[oore] to Washington Irving, n. d.; ALS, 1 p. w/addr
  - Thomas Moore to Washington Irving, n. d.; AN, 1 p.
    written on a calling card
  - T[homas] Moore to Washington Irving, n. d.; ALS, 1 p. w/addr
    encl. ALS, no date, Thomas Longman to Thomas Moore
- Miscellaneous
  - Washington Irving, head and shoulders, signed, 1851; Etching,
  - 17 postcards and printed photos showing New York City, ca. 1739-1800, Prints
  - Canadian penny token, 1843; Currency,
  - United States ten-cent bill, 1849; Currency,
  - Sate of Virginia $5.00, 1858; Currency,
  - Confederate States of America $100.00, 1863; Bond,
  - Confederate States of America $20.00, 1864; Currency,
  - Power of Attorney, Washington Irving to Pierre Irving, 1842 Apr 21; ADS, 4 p.
  - Assignment of copyright to Pierre Irving for Washington Irving's Life of George Washington, 1860 Feb 10; ADS, 3 p.
  - Release of Pierre Irving from further accounting as executor of Washington Irving's will, by Sarah Irving and Catherine Irving, 1869 Mar 30; ADS, 2 p.
  - Passport for Frederick Libbey(pre-printed part), 1908 Mar 18; ADS, 1 p.
  - Autographs of Edward Everett, George Bancroft, William Seward, Robert Winthrop, and Martin Van Buren, ADS
  - 12 clippings regarding Washington Irving, 1876-1919; Printed,
  - Translation of magazine article from the Border Magazine, regarding Irving family, 1903 Sep; AM,
  - List of home remedies, in an unknown hand, AM
  - 2 unidentified fragments, n. d.; AMs,